Guide to the Charles Humboldt Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Charles Humboldt papers
1935-1963
MS 721
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4
(9 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, research materials, and other papers of Charles Humboldt (also known as Clarence Weinstock), left-wing editor, poet and critic. Humboldt was variously connected with Art Front, New Masses, Masses and Mainstream, and the National Guardian, and much of the correspondence deals with the policies, finances, and problems of left-wing journals. Correspondents include Alvah Bessie, Ralph Ellison, Lillian Hellman, Kenneth Tynan, Christina Stead, Scott Nearing, and Linus Pauling.
Humboldt, Charles, 1910-1964
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Louis B. Schwartz, 1972.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Correspondence. II. Writings and Research. III. Personal and Financial.
Scope and Contents
Charles Humboldt (1910-1964) was a left-wing editor, poet and critic of art and literature. His true name was not Charles Humboldt but Clarence Weinstock, and Clarence Weinstock is the name under which he published articles in the 1930s, served in the United States Army in the 1940s, and paid taxes until his death in 1964. Charles Humboldt is the name under which he wrote between the late 1930s and the 1960s and under which he gained his reputation as an editor, critic and poet. Between 1935 and 1964 he was one of the editors, successively, of Art Front, the New Masses, Masses and Mainstream, and the National Guardian.
The first series of Humboldt's papers consists of his correspondence for the period 1946-1963. In his capacity as an editor and critic, Humboldt corresponded with many left-wing writers. Included among them are: Alvaro Cardona-Hine, Ralph Ellison, Lillian Hellman, Renaud de Jouvenel, Walter Lowenfels, Scott Nearing, Sean O'Casey and Linus Pauling. Humboldt also carried on an extensive correspondence with Edith Anderson, Jack Beeching, Alvah Bessie, Maxim Lieber, Albert Maltz, Tom McGrath, and Philip Stevenson. Much of the correspondence -- particularly that with Lee Baxandall, John Berger, J. D. Bernal, A. Beison, Louis Burnham, Emile Burns and Annette Rubenstein -- deals with the policies, finances and problems of left-wing journals. There is also important correspondence with the Soviet periodicals Foreign Literature, Soviet Culture and Soviet Literature.
Although in the CORRESPONDENCE series no distinction has been made between letters written by or to Charles Humboldt and Clarence Weinstock, in the WRITINGS AND RESEARCH MATERIALS series his writings under the two names are separately arranged. The Writings includes not only stories, reviews, poetry and dramas by Charles Humboldt and Clarence Weinstock, but also a large number by other left-wing authors and poets. Also in the WRITINGS AND RESEARCH MATERIALS series is a long unpublished article by Charles Humboldt on the new critics and an unfinished manuscript by Clarence Weinstock on the Mexican muralists. The PERSONAL AND FINANCIAL series, also divided into separate sections for the names Charles Humboldt and Clarence Weinstock, contains biographical material and memorabilia.
Mrs Miriam Humboldt Schwartz, widow of Charles Humboldt, with her husband Louis B. Schwartz donated these papers to Yale University in 1972.
Biographical / Historical
Charles Humboldt (whose real name was Clarence Weinstock) was born in 1910 and raised in New York City. In 1925, at the age of fifteen, he left high school and travelled around the United States. Later that same year he went to Paris to study painting and there decided that his major interest was in the field of art criticism.
Humboldt returned from Europe in 1934 and became assistant editor of New Masses, and eventually editor of the artists' union bulletin published by the WPA federal art project group. During the late Thirties he was associate and then managing editor of Art Front, an art magazine written and published by artists. Contributors to this monthly publication included Picasso, Leger, Lurcat, Max Weber, Stuart Davis, Ben Shahn, Raphael and Moses Soyer, Jack Levine, Philip Evergood and Arshile Gorky.
During World War II, Charles Humboldt served in the U.S. Army on the Italian front. He began as a cryptographer but was transferred to Information and Education where he prepared bulletins and booklets on the progress of the war and on postwar perspectives.
After the war ended, Humboldt returned to the United States and from 1946 to 1947 was assistant public relations director for the Palestine Foundation Fund. He also became editor of the cultural quarterly Mainstream, which in 1947 merged with the New Masses and became known as Masses and Mainstream. In 1948 he joined Citadel Press as an editor and publicist, a position he held until 1952.
During a trip to Mexico in 1952-1953, Humboldt met the prominent mural painters Rivera, Siqueiros and Leopoldo Mendez. Influenced by his friendship with these artists, he began to work on an iconography of Mexican mural painting but ill health forced him to abandon the project.
Returning to New York, Humboldt became editor of Translations, a bureau serving leading publishers, corporations, and scientific institutions with translations of scientific and technical subjects, as well as literature and fine arts. In 1956 he turned to free lance writing, mainly in the medical field. Humboldt wrote for Scope Weekly and for the pharmaceutical firms of Smith, Kline and French and Purdue Frederick.
Since the end of World War II, Humboldt had edited - at times single-handedly - the left-wing magazine Masses and Mainstream. In 1960 he left this quarterly and became book editor of the National Guardian, a position he held until his death on January 23, 1964.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
National Guardian; New Masses; Art; Communism; Journalism; Radicalism; Socialism; Europe; Soviet Union; Editors; Anderson, Edith, 1915-; Barnum, Thomas J.; Baxandall, Lee; Beeching, Jack, 1922-; Berger, John, 1926-2017; Bernal, J. D. (John Desmond), 1901-1971; Bessie, Alvah Cecil, 1904-1985; Biberman, H. J. (Herbert J.); Brand, Millen, 1906-1980; Burnham, Louis E., 1915-1960; Burus, Emile; Cameron, Angus; Cardona-Hine, Alvaro, 1926-; Castro, Fidel, 1926-2016; Ellison, Ralph, 1914-1994; Fast, Howard, 1914-2003; Hellman, Lillian, 1905-1984; Hughes, Langston, 1902-1967; Humboldt, Charles, 1910-1964; Jouvenel, Renaud de, 1907-; Lardner, Ring, Jr., 1915-2000; Lieber, Maxim, 1897-1993; Lowenfels, Walter, 1897-1976; Maltz, Albert, 1908-1985; McGrath, Thomas, 1916-1990; Nearing, Scott, 1883-1983; Nelson, Truman, 1911-1987; O'Casey, Sean, 1880-1964; Pauling, Linus, 1901-1994; Perlo, Victor, 1912-; Rabinowitz, Victor, 1911-2007; Rubenstein, Annette T.; Stead, Christina, 1902-1983; Stevenson, Philip; Struik, Dirk J. (Dirk Jan), 1894-2000; Trumbo, Dalton, 1905-1976; Tynan, Kenneth, 1927-1980
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1946-1963; Series I; 1.25 linear feet (3 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  The CORRESPONDENCE series includes letters addressed to Charles Humboldt (Clarence Weinstock). The folders are arranged alphabetically by the name of the correspondent and, in a few cases, by the name of a periodical. The folders of Edith Anderson, Ruth Bartlett, M. Millen Brand, Ring Lardner, Jr., Walter Lowenfels, and John Sanford, contain writings attached to their covering-letters.
  - Ab - Ax (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General
    Letters To CH/From CH: (3/6)
  - Abzug, Martin, 1954, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (1/2)
  - Ackerman, Barbara, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ambatielos, Betty, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (0/1)
  - Anderson, Edith, 1956-1961, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (63/38)
  - Ba - Bu (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Babb, Sanora, 1951-1952, 1954, 1956, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (4/2)
  - Baer, Stan, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (2/0)
    - Abbe, George, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Baker, Lou, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (2/2)
  - Barnum, Thomas J., 1958 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (16/3)
  - Baxandall, Judith, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (2/1)
  - Baxandall, Lee, 1959-1960, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (14/2)
  - Bay, I. H., 1956 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (1/1)
  - Beaching, Jack, 1956-1959, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (30/15)
  - Berger, John, 1956-1959 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (14/18)
  - Barges, Ruth, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bernal, J. D., 1957 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bernard, John T., 1956 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (1/4)
  - Berson, A., 1956 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Bessie, Alvah, 1947, 1956-1957, 1959, 1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (17/7)
  - Biberman, Herbert, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Black, Henry, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Blair, Fred, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Blake, Christina (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (9/3)
  - Blake, William, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Block, Haskell, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Bonosky, Philip, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (3/1)
  - Bradbury, Ray, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Braden, Anne, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Brand, M. Millen, 1947, 1955, 1959, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (4/0)
  - Bratt, George, 1956-1957, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (2/4)
  - Brewer, W. D., 1958, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Brown, Lloyd, 1952, 1954, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Burnham, Louis, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Burns, Emile, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Ca - Cu (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Cabral, Olga, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (0/2)
  - Cameron, Angus, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Cardona-Hine, Alvaro, 1957-1963 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (27/16)
  - Carter, Martin, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (2/3)
  - Casetta, Mario, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (2/9)
  - Castro, Fidel, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Chacon, Juan, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Chametzky, Jules, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Chang, Kuo Wei, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Chen Han-seng, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Cheng, T. K., 1956 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Cogswell, Fred, 1956, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Cohen, Robert S., 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Cole, Lester, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (1/6)
  - Corbett, James, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Cronin, Kathleen, 1956, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (1/13)
  - D - Du (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Davis, Marian, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Ed (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Ellison, Ralph, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (1/0)
  - Evergood, Philip, 1956, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (3/0)
  - Fast, Howard, 1956, 1958
    See: box 2, folder 69
  - Fi - Fr (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Field, Ben, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Finkelstein, Sidney, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Foreign Literature, 1959-1960, undated (Box 2, Folder 60)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (5/2)
  - Ge - Go (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Ha - He (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Hellman, Lillian, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Hill, Christopher, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Hitchcock, George, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Horn, Hershel, undated (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Hughes, Langston, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Ji - Jo (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - de Jouvenel, Renaud, 1956, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (4/1)
  - Ka - Ku (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - King, Philip, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Krchmarek, Jean, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Kyle, Frank, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Le (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Landau, Saul, 1952, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Landis, Arthur, [1960?], 1961 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Lardner, Ring, Jr., 1958 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Lawson, Jack, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Lieber, Maxim, 1955-1963 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (30/16)
  - Lindsay, Jack, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Lohr, George, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Lowenfels, Walter, 1962, undated (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Lund, Mary G., undated (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Ma - Mu (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Magil, Abe, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Maltz, Albert, 1947, 1955-1959, undated (Box 2, Folder 86)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (31/11)
  - Maltz, Margaret, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Martin, David, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Martynova, A.
    See: box 3, folder 107
  - Matveyeva, Nina
    See: box 3, folder 108
  - May, James B.
    See:box 3, folder 114
  - McGrath, Tom, 1952, 1964, undated (Box 2, Folder 88)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (18/1)
  - Mistram, S. A., 1954-1956, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - Moses, Morris, 1957, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - Ne - Ni (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - Nearing, Scott, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - Nearing, Helen, 1956, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - Nelson, Truman, 1957-1960 (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - New Masses Anthology (Box 3, Folder 94)
    See also: box 1, folder 20
    See also: box 1, folder 29
    See also: box 2, folder 55
    See also: box 2, folder 63
    See also: box 2, folder 67
    See also: box 2, folder 86
    See also: box 3, folder 110
    See also: box 3, folder 111
    See also: box 3, folder 112
  - Norton, William, 1956-1957, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 95)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (4/3)
  - O'Casey, Sean, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - Orlova, Ryessa
    See: box 2, folder 60
  - Pa - Pr (Box 3, Folder 97)
  - Pauling, Linus, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - Perlo, Victor, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 99)
  - Ra - Ro (Box 3, Folder 100)
  - Rabinowitz, Victor, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 101)
  - Reed, Alma M., 1956, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 102)
  - Rubenstein, Annette, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 103)
  - Sa - St (Box 3, Folder 104)
  - Sanford, John, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 105)
  - Schlauch, Margaret, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 106)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (7/0)
  - Shirokov, O.
  - Soviet Culture, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 107)
  - Soviet Literature, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 108)
  - Stead, Christina, 1956-1958 (Box 3, Folder 109)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (6/0)
  - Stevenson, Philip, 1947, 1952, 1955-1963 (Box 3, Folder 110)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (46/24)
  - Struik, Dirk, 1947, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 111)
  - Swallow, Alan, 1946-1948 (Box 3, Folder 112)
    See also: New Masses Anthology
  - Ta - Tu (Box 3, Folder 113)
  - Trace, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 114)
  - Trumbo, Dalton, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 115)
  - Trushechenko, E.
  - Tynan, Kenneth, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 116)
  - Wa - Wo (Box 3, Folder 117)
  - Waterman, Ray, 1959-1960, undated (Box 3, Folder 118)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (8/5)
  - Wortis, Avi, 1960, undated (Box 3, Folder 119)
  - Yeh Chun-Chien, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 120)
  - Zivkovic, Peter, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 121)
    Letters To CH/From CH: (2/5)
  - Zweig, Arnold, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 122)
  - Unidentified correspondents (Box 3, Folder 123)
- WRITINGS AND RESEARCH MATERIALS, 1935-1963; Series II; 2 linear feet (5 boxes)
  WRITINGS AND RESEARCH MATERIALS consists of manuscripts, printed writings, poetry and notes and is divided into three major subsections: (a) the writings of Charles Humboldt, (b) the writings of Clarence Weinstock, and (c) the writings of others.
  Within each section, writings are subdivided into prose and poetry, and then into published and unpublished writings. With the exceptions of Clarence Weinstock's work on the Mexican muralists and some of Charles Humboldt's short stories and poetry, most of these writings are in printed form. Writings and related research materials are filed together for both Charles Humboldt and Clarence Weinstock. Folders within these subsections are arranged alphabetically by the title of the work.
  Writings of others includes fiction, drama, poetry and reviews collected by Charles Humboldt or submitted to him for consideration for the New Masses, Masses and Mainstream, Mainstream ,and the National Guardian. This section is arranged alphabetically by the author's name. In a few cases, writings of others have been filed in the CORRESPONDENCE series under the name of the writer of the cover letter. This occurs in the correspondence of Edith Anderson, Ruth Bartlett, M. Millen Brand, Ring Lardner, Jr., Walter Lowenfels, and John Sanford.
  - Charles Humboldt - Writings (Published)
    - "Again - The Book Burners", 1946 (Box 4, Folder 124)
    - "Algeria's Future", 1961 (Box 4, Folder 124)
    - "American Atrocity", 1946 (Box 4, Folder 125)
    - Die amerikanischen Präsidentschaftswahlen, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 126)
    - "Angry Man", 1949 (Box 4, Folder 127)
    - "Art in Wartime", 1941 (Box 4, Folder 128)
    - "The Art of Ingmar Bergman", 1963 (Box 4, Folder 129)
    - "The Art of Lu Hsun", 1957 (Box 4, Folder 130)
    - "The Atkinson Formula", 1946 (Box 4, Folder 131)
    - "Bergman's Screen Plays", 1961 (Box 4, Folder 132)
    - "The Best Kind of Critic", 1947 (Box 4, Folder 132)
    - "The Betrayal of France", 1941 (Box 4, Folder 133)
    - "Boardman Robinson", 1946 (Box 4, Folder 134)
    - "Carl Mazzini's Political Novel", 1959 (Box 4, Folder 135)
    - "The Case of Doctor Zhivago", 1958 (Box 4, Folder 136)
    - "Chekov's Life", 1962 (Box 4, Folder 136)
    - "The Coming American Elections", undated (Box 4, Folder 137)
    - "Communists in Novels", 1949 (Box 4, Folder 138)
    - "A Day at the Shop", 1946 (Box 4, Folder 139)
    - "A Day with Ivan Denisovich", 1963 (Box 4, Folder 139)
    - "Deutscher on Russia Today", 1960 (Box 4, Folder 139)
    - "Diary of Darkness", 1962 (Box 4, Folder 140)
    - "Distinguished Issue", 1942 (Box 4, Folder 140)
    - "Dramatic Ambiguity (?)", undated (Box 4, Folder 141)
    - "Dramatic Reportage", 1941 (Box 4, Folder 142)
    - "Dubious Conclusions", 1941 (Box 4, Folder 143)
    - "Dubious Steinbeck", 1961 (Box 4, Folder 143)
    - "Fadayev", 1956 (Box 4, Folder 144)
    - "Fiction on the Left", 1957 (Box 4, Folder 145)
    - "A Film About Nazis - For Americans", 1961 (Box 4, Folder 146)
    - "Films", 1947 (Box 4, Folder 146)
    - "A Fine First Novel", 1962 (Box 4, Folder 146)
    - "Florentine Story", 1949 (Box 4, Folder 147)
    - "Fourteen Years Later" (fragment), 1958 (Box 4, Folder 148)
    - "Freedom and Responsibility", 1950 (Box 4, Folder 149)
    - "Good Will is Not Enough", 1959 (Box 4, Folder 150)
    - "Ham Actor", 1946 (Box 4, Folder 151)
    - "How Banal Can Evil Be?", 1963 (Box 4, Folder 152)
    - "How True is Fiction?", 1949 (Box 4, Folder 152)
    - "The Intransigent", 1962 (Box 4, Folder 153)
    - "An Irish Shout", 1949 (Box 4, Folder 153)
    - "It's Love and Love Alone", 1947 (Box 4, Folder 154)
    - "Jawaharlal Nehru", 1942 (Box 4, Folder 155)
    - "Lerner's Cold War Apologia", 1963 (Box 4, Folder 156)
    - "Lerner's Little Labor Lectures", 1946 (Box 4, Folder 156)
    - "A Living Voice", 1952 (Box 4, Folder 157)
    - "The Lost Cause of Robert Penn Warren", 1948 (Box 4, Folder 158)
    - "Lost Patrol", 1945 (Box 4, Folder 159)
    - "Louis Aragon, Great Communist Poet of the French Resistance", 1945 (Box 4, Folder 160)
    - "Lynching Bee - Northern Style", 1946 (Box 4, Folder 161)
    - "Mailer's Men", 1948 (Box 4, Folder 162)
    - "Report on Mainstream", 1958-1960 (Box 4, Folder 163)
    - "Man on the Road", 1952 (Box 4, Folder 164)
    - "Marquis a la Koestler", 1947 (Box 4, Folder 165)
    - "Maxim Gorky and Writers", 1946 (Box 4, Folder 166)
    - "Mexico's Angry Novelist", 1961 (Box 4, Folder 166)
    - "Mexico's Mural Painters", 1961 (Box 4, Folder 166)
    - "Mills on Marxists", 1962 (Box 4, Folder 166)
    - "A Misread Soviet Fable", 1961 (Box 4, Folder 167)
    - "Mist and Mysticism", 1941 (Box 4, Folder 167)
    - "More of O'Casey", 1953 (Box 4, Folder 168)
    - "More than Bad Manners", 1946 (Box 4, Folder 169)
    - "More Than Bread Alone", 1958 (Box 4, Folder 170)
    - "Mr. Cudahy's Excesses", 1941 (Box 4, Folder 171)
    - "Nest of Vipers", 1947 (Box 4, Folder 172)
    - "A New Novel By Baldwin", 1962 (Box 4, Folder 172)
    - "No Art is Neutral", 1953 (Box 4, Folder 173)
    - "No Hard Feelings", 1958-1960 (Box 4, Folder 174)
    - "A Novel is Born", 1961 (Box 4, Folder 175)
    - "The Novel of Action", 1947 (Box 4, Folder 175)
    - "On Politics and Culture", 1956 (Box 5, Folder 176)
    - "Orozco's Own Story", 1962 (Box 5, Folder 176)
    - "Osborne Looks at Luther", 1962 (Box 5, Folder 176)
    - "Our Own Kind", undated (Box 5, Folder 177)
    - "Paul Draper's Art", 1942 (Box 5, Folder 178)
    - "The Peace Issue in the American Elections", undated (Box 5, Folder 179)
    - "Polish Marxist, Soviet Poet Look at 'Freedom'", 1963 (Box 5, Folder 179)
    - "The Porter Novel", 1962 (Box 5, Folder 179)
    - "Reactionary Day-Dream", 1942 (Box 5, Folder 180)
    - "The Russians at War", 1963 (Box 5, Folder 180)
    - "The Salt of Freedom", 1956 (Box 5, Folder 181)
    - "Sartre on Freedom and History", 1960 (Box 5, Folder 181)
    - "Sheep's Flight", 1942 (Box 5, Folder 182)
    - "Silent Troopship", 1946 (Box 5, Folder 183)
    - "Soviet Power", 1941 (Box 5, Folder 184)
    - "The Spectator", 1960-1962 (Box 5, Folder 185)
    - "A Squint at History", 1942 (Box 5, Folder 186)
    - "Steel Worker's Son", 1953 (Box 5, Folder 187)
    - "Sweet Mystery of Life", 1947 (Box 5, Folder 188)
    - "Taking Stock", 1948 (Box 5, Folder 189)
    - "Teacher Needs More Than An Apple", 1946 (Box 5, Folder 190)
    - "Lesson For Teachers", 1946 (Box 5, Folder 190)
    - "Teddy Roosevelt Had His Number", 1947 (Box 5, Folder 191)
    - "Three Kinds of Fiction", 1947 (Box 5, Folder 192)
    - "Thriller Psychosis", 1945 (Box 5, Folder 193)
    - "To Die -", 1945 (Box 5, Folder 194)
    - "Tolstoy and Art", 1950 (Box 5, Folder 195)
    - "Too Smooth", 1958 (Box 5, Folder 196)
    - "To the Mad Hatters", 1947 (Box 5, Folder 197)
    - "The Tragedy of Dylan Thomas", 1954 (Box 5, Folder 198)
    - "Trial by Stoolpigeon", 1949 (Box 5, Folder 199)
    - "A Trotskyite in Love", 1946 (Box 5, Folder 200)
    - "Trouble on the Farm", undated (Box 5, Folder 201)
    - "Two Fighters", 1942 (Box 5, Folder 202)
    - "The Uninquiring Reporter", 1941 (Box 5, Folder 203)
    - "The Users", 1945 (Box 5, Folder 204)
    - "A Victory for Civil Liberties", undated (Box 5, Folder 205)
    - "Viva it Primo Maggio!", 1946 (Box 5, Folder 206)
    - "The Voice Persisted Until Death", 1962 (Box 5, Folder 207)
    - "The Voices of the Slum", 1961 (Box 5, Folder 207)
    - "What is Freedom?", 1950 (Box 5, Folder 208)
    - "What Price Movie?", 1948 (Box 5, Folder 209)
    - "What's Wrong With our Short Stories?", 1947 (Box 5, Folder 210)
    - "Who Won the Steel Strike?", undated (Box 5, Folder 211)
    - "Why Teacher Leaves School", 1946 (Box 5, Folder 212)
    - "The World of Bertolt Brecht", 1960 (Box 5, Folder 212)
    - Untitled review of Philip Van Doren Stern's The Drums of Morning, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 213)
    - Untitled review of Diego Rivera's My Art, My Life, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 214)
    - Untitled review of Jean Genet's Lady of the Flowers, undated (Box 5, Folder 214)
    - Untitled review of MacKinley Helm's Man of Fire: J. C. Orozco, undated (Box 5, Folder 214)
    - Untitled review of Jean Berger's A Painter of Our Time, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 215)
    - Untitled review of Leon Howard's Victorian Knight-Errant, 1954 (Box 5, Folder 216)
    - Untitled review of Edward Albee's "Who's Afraid of Virginia Woolf?", undated (Box 5, Folder 217)
    - Lists of writings (Box 5, Folder 218)
  - Charles Humboldt - Writings (Unpublished)
    - "A's Story", undated (Box 6, Folder 219)
    - "The Artificial Birds", [1951?] (Box 6, Folder 220)
    - "The Gravedigger", undated (Box 6, Folder 221)